<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" specific-use="sps-1.5" xml:lang="en">
	<front>
		<journal-meta>
			<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz</journal-id>
			<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">mioc</journal-id>
			<journal-title-group>
				<journal-title>Memórias do Instituto Oswaldo Cruz</journal-title>
				<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">Mem. Inst. Oswaldo
					Cruz</abbrev-journal-title>
			</journal-title-group>
			<issn pub-type="ppub">0074-0276</issn>
			<issn pub-type="epub">1678-8060</issn>
			<publisher>
				<publisher-name>Instituto Oswaldo Cruz, Ministério da Saúde</publisher-name>
			</publisher>
		</journal-meta>
		<article-meta>
			<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/0074-02760160042</article-id>
			<article-categories>
				<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
					<subject>Articles</subject>
				</subj-group>
			</article-categories>
			<title-group>
				<article-title>Analysis of the genetic diversity of <italic>Candida</italic>
					isolates obtained from diabetic patients and kidney transplant
					recipients</article-title>
			</title-group>
			<contrib-group>
				<contrib contrib-type="author">
					<name>
						<surname>Benedetti</surname>
						<given-names>Volmir Pitt</given-names>
					</name>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
				</contrib>
				<contrib contrib-type="author">
					<name>
						<surname>Savi</surname>
						<given-names>Daiani Cristina</given-names>
					</name>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
				</contrib>
				<contrib contrib-type="author">
					<name>
						<surname>Aluizio</surname>
						<given-names>Rodrigo</given-names>
					</name>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
				</contrib>
				<contrib contrib-type="author">
					<name>
						<surname>Adamoski</surname>
						<given-names>Douglas</given-names>
					</name>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
				</contrib>
				<contrib contrib-type="author">
					<name>
						<surname>Kava-Cordeiro</surname>
						<given-names>Vanessa</given-names>
					</name>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
				</contrib>
				<contrib contrib-type="author">
					<name>
						<surname>Galli-Terasawa</surname>
						<given-names>Lygia V</given-names>
					</name>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
				</contrib>
				<contrib contrib-type="author">
					<name>
						<surname>Glienke</surname>
						<given-names>Chirlei</given-names>
					</name>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
				</contrib>
			</contrib-group>
			<aff id="aff1">
				<label>1</label>
				<institution content-type="original">Universidade Paranaense, Departamento de
					Microbiologia, Francisco Beltrão, PR, Brasil</institution>
				<institution content-type="normalized">Universidade Paranaense</institution>
				<institution content-type="orgname">Universidade Paranaense</institution>
				<institution content-type="orgdiv1">Departamento de Microbiologia</institution>
				<addr-line>
					<named-content content-type="city">Francisco Beltrão</named-content>
					<named-content content-type="state">PR</named-content>
				</addr-line>
				<country country="BR">Brazil</country>
			</aff>
			<aff id="aff2">
				<label>2</label>
				<institution content-type="original">Universidade Federal do Paraná, Departamento de
					Patologia Básica, Curitiba, PR, Brasil</institution>
				<institution content-type="normalized">Universidade Federal do Paraná</institution>
				<institution content-type="orgname">Universidade Federal do Paraná</institution>
				<institution content-type="orgdiv1">Departamento de Patologia Básica</institution>
				<addr-line>
					<named-content content-type="city">Curitiba</named-content>
					<named-content content-type="state">PR</named-content>
				</addr-line>
				<country country="BR">Brazil</country>
			</aff>
			<aff id="aff3">
				<label>3</label>
				<institution content-type="original">Universidade Federal do Paraná, Departamento de
					Genética, Curitiba, PR, Brasil</institution>
				<institution content-type="normalized">Universidade Federal do Paraná</institution>
				<institution content-type="orgname">Universidade Federal do Paraná</institution>
				<institution content-type="orgdiv1">Departamento de Genética</institution>
				<addr-line>
					<named-content content-type="city">Curitiba</named-content>
					<named-content content-type="state">PR</named-content>
				</addr-line>
				<country country="BR">Brazil</country>
			</aff>
			<pub-date pub-type="epub">
				<year>2017</year>
			</pub-date>
			<fpage>00</fpage>
			<lpage>00</lpage>
			<history>
				<date date-type="received">
					<day>08</day>
					<month>02</month>
					<year>2016</year>
				</date>
				<date date-type="accepted">
					<day>16</day>
					<month>05</month>
					<year>2016</year>
				</date>
			</history>
			<permissions>
				<license license-type="open-access"
					xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xml:lang="en">
					<license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the
						Creative Commons Attribution License</license-p>
				</license>
			</permissions>
			<abstract>
				<title>Abstract:</title>
				<p>Yeasts of the genus Candida have high genetic variability and are the most common
					opportunistic pathogenic fungi in humans. In this study, we evaluated the
					genetic diversity among 120 isolates of Candida spp. obtained from diabetic
					patients, kidney transplant recipients and patients without any immune
					deficiencies from Paraná state, Brazil. The analysis was performed using the
					ITS1-5.8S-ITS2 region and a partial sequence of 28S rDNA. In the phylogenetic
					analysis, we observed a consistent separation of the species C. albicans, C.
					dubliniensis, C. glabrata, C. tropicalis, C. parapsilosis, C. metapsilosis and
					C. orthopsilosis, however with low intraspecific variability. In the analysis of
					the C. albicans species, two clades were formed. Clade A included the largest
					number of isolates (91.2%) and the majority of isolates from GenBank (71.4%).
					The phylogenetic analysis showed low intraspecific genetic diversity, and the
					genetic polymorphisms between C. albicans isolates were similar to genetic
					divergence found in other studies performed with isolates from Brazil. This low
					genetic diversity of isolates can be explained by the geographic proximity of
					the patients evaluated. It was observed that yeast colonisation was highest in
					renal transplant recipients and diabetic patients and that C. albicans was the
					species most frequently isolated.</p>
			</abstract>
			<kwd-group xml:lang="en">
				<title>Key words:</title>
				<kwd>ITS1-5.8S-ITS2 and 28S rDNA</kwd>
				<kwd>Candida</kwd>
				<kwd>diabetes</kwd>
				<kwd>renal transplant recipient</kwd>
			</kwd-group>
			<funding-group>
				<award-group>
					<funding-source>University of Chile</funding-source>
					<award-id>1140824</award-id>
				</award-group>
			</funding-group>
		</article-meta>
	</front>
	<body>
		<p>Infections caused by opportunistic fungi, such as <italic>Candida</italic> yeast, often
			affect patients undergoing organ or bone marrow transplants, AIDS patients, patients
			taking immunosuppressive drugs, patients undergoing cancer treatment, those having
			undergone major surgery, those of advanced age or premature infants (<xref
				ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Anderson et al. 2007</xref>). It can also affect
			individuals suffering from chronic stress, patients with metabolic diseases such as
			diabetes, those who are malnourished and those taking broad-spectrum antibiotics (<xref
				ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Fagan 1999</xref>).</p>
		<p>The majority of fungal infections in humans are caused by the species <italic>C.
				albicans</italic> and <italic>C. glabrata</italic>. The prevalence rates of
				<italic>C. albicans</italic> and <italic>C. glabrata</italic> infections are
			approximately 70% and 15%, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Anderson et al.
				2007</xref>). Infections caused by non-<italic>albicans Candida</italic> (NAC)
			species, such as <italic>C. tropicalis</italic>, <italic>C. parapsilosis</italic>,
				<italic>C. krusei</italic>, <italic>C. lusitaniae</italic>, <italic>C.
				inconspicua</italic>, <italic>C. lipolytica</italic> and <italic>C.
				norvegensis</italic>, have become increasingly more frequent; in some cases,
			infections with NAC species are predominant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Fagan
				1999</xref>). There is great genetic diversity among different yeast species, in
			particular <italic>C. albicans</italic>, and this characteristic may be explained by the
			presence of a diploid genome, predominantly clonal reproduction and a high rate of
			recombination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
		<p>
			<fig id="f1">
				<label>Figure 1</label>
				<caption>
					<title>Bayesian inference phylogenetic tree of Candida albicans isolates and
						reference strains generated using ITS1-5.8S-ITS2 of rDNA sequences.
						Bootstrap values of máximum likelihood and Bayesian posterior probability
						values are shown above nodes.</title>
				</caption>
				<graphic xlink:href="1678-8060-mioc-0074-02760160042-gf01.tif"/>
			</fig>
		</p>
		<p>In the present study, we evaluated the genetic diversity among <italic>C.
				albicans</italic> isolates from diabetic patients and kidney transplant recipients
			and compared them to other isolates described in the literature. We also determined
			which species of <italic>Candida</italic> were involved in the colonisation of the oral
			cavity in diabetic patients and renal transplant recipients from southern Paraná state
			(Brazil), including with what frequency colonisation occurred. We also evaluated the
			intraspecific diversity of <italic>C. albicans</italic> and its population
			structure.</p>
		<sec sec-type="materials|methods">
			<title>Materials and Methods</title>
			<p>Patients analysed - In total, 190 individuals were analysed, of which 64 were
				diabetic patients, 37 were kidney transplant recipients, and 89 had no immune
				deficiencies (control group). The diabetic patients were over 40 years old, had been
				diagnosed with type II diabetes for over five years, were not using insulin and had
				hypertension; 48 had hyperglycaemia. All transplant patients were over 30 years old
				and had a kidney transplant over one year ago; 19 patients were on the
				immunosuppressant prednisone. The control group was composed of people who were
				between the ages of 18 and 30, were not being treated for any disease and were not
				using drugs with antimicrobial or anti-inflammatory activities. An epidemiological
				survey of the patients was also performed to obtain more information.</p>
			<p>Sample processing - Approximately 1 mL of saliva was collected from each patient
				according to the no stimulation method described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5"
					>Cartajena et al. 2007</xref>). After collection, 100 mL of saliva was
				inoculated in CHROagar&#x00ae; medium (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Gambier
					1993</xref>) and incubated at 25ºC for five online | memorias.ioc.fiocruz.br
				days. After incubation, the colony-forming units per mL saliva (CFU/mL) were
				determined. An initial screening of Candida was performed to assess biochemical
				assimilation (auxonograma), sugar fermentation (zymogram) and production of germ
				tubes (Gambier 1993). Isolates were maintained by inoculating in Brain Heart
				Infusion medium (Difco) containing 20% glycerol in Eppendorf tubes and storing at
				-20ºC (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Kim et al. 2002</xref>).</p>
			<p>Isolates and reference strains - The present study examined 120 yeast species
				isolated from 96 patients out of a 190-patient pool. The following reference Candida
				strains from the American Type Culture Collection (ATCC) were also used: C. albicans
				ATCC 44858, C. glabrata ATCC 2001 and C. tropicalis ATCC 28707. This research was
				approved by the Ethics Committee under registration number CAAE-0200.1.375.000-11 -
				Paranaense University, Paraná (PR, Brazil) <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure
					2</xref>.</p>
			<p>
				<fig id="f2">
					<label>Figure 2</label>
					<caption>
						<title>Bayesian inference phylogenetic tree of seven Candida species. The
							tree was built using concatenated sequences of the ITS and 28S
							genes</title>
					</caption>
					<graphic xlink:href="1678-8060-mioc-0074-02760160042-gf02.tif"/>
				</fig>
			</p>
		</sec>
		<sec sec-type="methods">
			<title>Land and Analysis Methods</title>
			<p><italic>Amplification of the ITS1, 5.8S, ITS2 and 28S rDNA regions</italic> - The
				primers V9G (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Buc y Silvestre 2006</xref>; <xref
					ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Johnson 1985</xref>) and ITS4 (<xref ref-type="bibr"
					rid="B8">Hogg et al. 2013</xref>) were used to amplify the Internal Transcribed
				Spacer (ITS) regions and 5.8S rDNA. The primers LR0R and LR5 were used to amplify
				fragments of 28S rDNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Andrefsky 1998</xref>), see
					<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3"
					>3</xref>. Polymerase chain reaction (PCR) reactions were performed in a total
				volume of 25 &#x00b5;L, which contained Tris Base buffer solution (pH 8.4) (20 mM),
				KCl (50 mM), deoxynucleotide triphosphates (dNTPs) (0.3 mM) (Invitrogen-Life
				Technologies, Brazil), MgCl<sub>2</sub> (1.6 mM), primers (15 pmol each), Taq DNA
				polymerase (0.5 U) (Invitrogen-Life Technologies, Brazil) and template DNA (20 ng).
				The amplification of the ITS regions and the 5.8S gene was performed using the
				following protocol: 95ºC for 5 min; 30 cycles of 95ºC for 1 min, 57ºC for 1 min, and
				72ºC for 1 min; and a final step at 72ºC for 5 min. The amplification of the 28S
				region was performed according to the following protocol: 95ºC for 5 min; 30 cycles
				at 95ºC for 1 min, 48ºC for 1 min, and 72ºC for 1 min; and a final step at 72ºC for
				5 min. <italic>PCR product purification</italic> - The PCR products (25 &#x00b5;L)
				were purified using 7.5 M ammonium acetate (15 &#x00b5;L) and absolute ethanol (74
				&#x00b5;L). Samples were incubated on ice for 1 h, followed by centrifugation for 45
				min at 23,100 g. The pellet was suspended in 12 &#x00b5;L of MilliQ water.</p>
			<p><italic>rDNA sequencing</italic> - Sequencing of the PCR products was performed using
				an ET Kit according to the manufacturer’s instructions. The products of the
				sequencing reaction were purified using Sephadex<sup>&#x2122;</sup> G-50 Fine DNA
				Grade resin and subjected to analysis by electrophoresis in a MegaBACE (Amersham
					Biosciences<sup>&#x00ae;</sup>) automated DNA sequencer.</p>
			<p><italic>Phylogenetic analysis</italic> - BioEdit 7.1.9 (<xref ref-type="bibr"
					rid="B1">Andrefsky 1998</xref>) and MEGA 5.1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10"
					>Kim et al. 2002</xref>) software were used for sequence editing and alignment.
				GARLI (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Gambier 1993</xref>) software was used for the
				maximum likelihood phylogenetic analysis, and MrBayes v.3.2.1 (<xref ref-type="bibr"
					rid="B4">Buc y Silvestre 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Johnson
					1985</xref>) software was used for Bayesian inference analysis. A bootstrap
				procedure with 2,000 replicates was used to check node consistency. In the analyses
				of maximum likelihood and Bayesian inference, ModelTest software version 3.7
				(Andrefsky 2010) was used to create the evolutionary model. A phylogenetic tree was
				generated using sequences from 80 isolates, the ATCC - 44858 (KM361826) reference
				lineage, lineages from Paraná state [UFPR - HC04IC (KJ651886)] and from São Paulo
				state (USP - ICB945 (JX463265), UFC - CA1150 (AB861482), UNICAMP - CA70 (DQ141236),
				UNESP - CA15 (KF385990) and the UNIFESP isolates LEMI7986E (KC905077) and L8278
				(KC408953). The sequence from the type strain CBS - 562 (NR125332) of <italic>C.
					albicans</italic> was also included in the analysis. All of the sequences
				analysed in this study were deposited. </p>
		</sec>
		<sec>
			<title>Black Ceiling: Context, Stratigraphy and Chronology</title>
			<p><italic>Epidemiological aspects of isolated yeast</italic> - Of the 190 patient
				samples, 96 (50.53%) contained yeast growth. A total of 120 strains belonging to the
				genus <italic>Candida</italic> were isolated from these 96 patient
					samples<italic>.</italic> Among the 37 samples from transplant recipients, yeast
				growth was observed in 19 (51.35%); the average CFU/mL of the saliva was 814. Among
				the 64 samples analysed from patients with diabetes, 44 (68.75%) contained yeast
				growth; the average CFU/mL was 932. In the control group (89 patients), growth was
				observed in 33 (37.08%) samples; the average CFU/mL of the saliva was 215. Of the
				120 isolates, 80 strains were identified as <italic>C. albicans</italic>, 17 as
					<italic>C. parapsilosis</italic>, eight as <italic>C. tropicalis</italic>, six
				as <italic>C. glabrata</italic>, four as <italic>C. dubliniensis</italic>, three as
					<italic>C. metapsilosis</italic> and two as <italic>C. orthopsilosis</italic>.
				The highest average CFU/ mL was observed in patients with diabetes and kidney
				transplants relative to the control group (p = 0.01). See <xref ref-type="fig"
					rid="f3">Figure 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4</xref>.</p>
			<p>
				<fig id="f3">
					<label>Figure 3</label>
					<caption>
						<title>Bootstrap values of maximum likelihood and Bayesian posterior
							probability values are shown above nodes</title>
					</caption>
					<graphic xlink:href="1678-8060-mioc-0074-02760160042-gf03.tif"/>
				</fig>
			</p>
			<p>
				<fig id="f4">
					<label>Figure 4</label>
					<caption>
						<title>Black Roof schematic views; A. longitudinal section (SW-NE); B.
							General plant excavated sectors, firebox (R2, R3, R4) and location of
							lithic tools (points); C. cross section (O-E).</title>
					</caption>
					<graphic xlink:href="1678-8060-mioc-0074-02760160042-gf04.tif"/>
				</fig>
			</p>
			<p>Average CFU/mL values were 879 for <italic>C. parapsilosis</italic>, 854 for
					<italic>C. tropicalis</italic>, 649 for <italic>C. albicans</italic>, 520 for
					<italic>C. glabrata</italic>, 55 for <italic>C. dubliniensis</italic>, 47 for
					<italic>C. metapsilosis</italic> and 25 for <italic>C. orthopsilosis</italic>.
				The analysis of patient interview data revealed that gender did not affect yeast
				growth, as the growth index was 24 (53.3%) among men and 72 (49.7%) among women (p =
				0.90). There was also no correlation found among the different age groups (&lt; 50
				years, 5160 years and &gt; 60 years) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4</xref>
				and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5</xref>) in terms of yeast isolation (p =
				0.09). Past candidiasis did not influence colonisation because yeast was isolated
				from 44 (45.8%) patients with a previous history of oral candidiasis and from 52
				(54.2%) of patients with no history of oral candidiasis (p = 0.13) in <xref
					ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>.</p>
			<table-wrap id="t1">
				<label>Table 1</label>
				<caption>
					<title>AMS 14C ages Roof Black (except * thermoluminescence with base year 2005)
						stratigraphically ordered. # Registration single plant.</title>
				</caption>
				<table>
					<colgroup width="12%">
						<col/>
						<col/>
						<col/>
						<col/>
						<col/>
						<col/>
						<col/>
						<col/>
					</colgroup>
					<thead style="background-color:#bebebe">
						<tr>
							<th align="left"># Lab</th>
							<th align="left">Excavation Unit</th>
							<th align="left">Rasgo</th>
							<th align="center">Feature </th>
							<th align="left"><sup>14</sup>C a.p.</th>
							<th align="left">&#x03b4;13C (‰)</th>
							<th align="left">Cal 2&#x03b4; a.p.</th>
							<th align="left">Material</th>
						</tr>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<tr>
							<td align="left">Beta 246499</td>
							<td align="left">A’2</td>
							<td align="left">Fogón (R2)</td>
							<td align="left">1 (0-5 cm)</td>
							<td align="left">1630 &#x00b1;40</td>
							<td align="left">-23,5</td>
							<td align="left">1400 a 1560</td>
							<td align="left">Carbón</td>
						</tr>
						<tr style="background-color:#f3f3f3">
							<td align="left">UCTL 1793</td>
							<td align="left">A1</td>
							<td align="left">-</td>
							<td align="left">2 (0-10 cm)</td>
							<td align="left">1190 &#x00b1;120*</td>
							<td align="left"> </td>
							<td align="left">895 a 1375</td>
							<td align="left">Cerámica</td>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td align="left">D-AMS 007241</td>
							<td align="left">C1</td>
							<td align="left">Asoc. #5</td>
							<td align="left">2 (5-10 cm)</td>
							<td align="left">2113 &#x00b1;28</td>
							<td align="left">-21,4</td>
							<td align="left">1900 a 2150</td>
							<td align="left">Carbón</td>
						</tr>
						<tr style="background-color:#f3f3f3">
							<td align="left">UGAMS 05343</td>
							<td align="left">A’1</td>
							<td align="left">Fogón (R4)</td>
							<td align="left">2 (5-10 cm)</td>
							<td align="left">6870 &#x00b1;30</td>
							<td align="left">-24,2</td>
							<td align="left">7590 a 7720</td>
							<td align="left">Carbón</td>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td align="left">Beta 246500</td>
							<td align="left">B3</td>
							<td align="left">Fogón (R3)</td>
							<td align="left">2 (10-15 cm)</td>
							<td align="left">5350 &#x00b1;40</td>
							<td align="left">-22,1</td>
							<td align="left">5990 a 6210</td>
							<td align="left">Carbón</td>
						</tr>
					</tbody>
				</table>
			</table-wrap>
			<p>
				<fig id="f5">
					<label>Figure 5</label>
					<caption>
						<title>Black Ceiling stratigraphic section calibrated ages; EU:
							stratigraphic unit.</title>
					</caption>
					<graphic xlink:href="1678-8060-mioc-0074-02760160042-gf05.tif"/>
				</fig>
			</p>
			<p><italic>Phylogenetic analysis</italic> - To determine the intraspecific variability
				among <italic>C. albicans</italic> isolates, our isolates were compared to sequences
				of <italic>C. albicans</italic> isolated from Brazil that were deposited in GenBank.
				In the ITS1-5.8SITS2 phylogenetic tree of <italic>C. albicans</italic> isolates
					(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5</xref>), we observed the possible
				formation of two population groups. Clade A consists of the largest number of
				isolates, including ATCC-44858, the type strain <italic>C. albicans</italic> -
				CBS562 and isolates from different Brazilian states including Paraná state
				(HC04IC/UFPR, KJ651886/GB), São Paulo state (ICB945/USP, JX463265/GB; CA70/UNICAMP,
				DQ141236/GB; and CA15/UNESP, KF385990/GB) and Ceará state (CA1150/UFC, AB861482/GB)
				(Neto et al. 2014) </p>
		</sec>
		<sec sec-type="materials">
			<title>Black Materials Ceiling sets</title>
			<sec>
				<title>Lithic Material</title>
				<p>Isolates belonging to Clade A had no genetic divergence in the ITS1-5.8S-ITS2
					rDNA region. The isolates with the highest genetic diversity were in Clade B
					(CA29PD, CA32PD, CA38PD, CA59PT, CA61PT, CA62PT, CA63PT and CA84PD).</p>
				<p>In the phylogenetic tree, assembled with 120 isolates belonging to seven
					different <italic>Candida</italic> species in which sequences from the ITS1 and
					ITS2 regions and the 5.8S and 28S rDNA genes were used, there is a consistent
					separation of the following species: <italic>C. albicans</italic>, <italic>C.
						dubliniensis</italic>, <italic>C. glabrata</italic>, <italic>C.
						tropicalis</italic> and the three species that formed the <italic>C.
						parapsilosis</italic> complex (<italic>C. parapsilosis</italic>, <italic>C.
						metapsilosis</italic> and <italic>C. orthopsilosis</italic>). Moreover, we
					were able to observe low intraspecific variability (<xref ref-type="table"
						rid="t2">Table 2</xref>).</p>
				<table-wrap id="t2">
					<label>Table 2</label>
					<caption>
						<title>Lithic sample according to their stratigraphic provenance. EU:
							stratigraphic unit. </title>
					</caption>
					<table>
						<colgroup width="16%">
							<col/>
							<col/>
							<col/>
							<col/>
							<col/>
							<col/>
						</colgroup>
						<thead style="background-color:#bebebe">
							<tr>
								<th align="left">Completeness</th>
								<th align="center">Surface</th>
								<th align="left">UE 1</th>
								<th align="left">UE 2</th>
								<th align="left">UE 3</th>
								<th align="left">Total</th>
							</tr>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<tr style="background-color:#f3f3f3">
								<td align="left">Full</td>
								<td align="center">2</td>
								<td align="left">248</td>
								<td align="left">575</td>
								<td align="left">19</td>
								<td align="left">844</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td align="left">Proximal</td>
								<td align="center">1</td>
								<td align="left">155</td>
								<td align="left">435</td>
								<td align="left">11</td>
								<td align="left">602</td>
							</tr>
							<tr style="background-color:#f3f3f3">
								<td align="left">Mesiodistal</td>
								<td align="center">8</td>
								<td align="left">1164</td>
								<td align="left">3305</td>
								<td align="left">80</td>
								<td align="left">4557</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td align="left">Total</td>
								<td align="center">11</td>
								<td align="left">1567</td>
								<td align="left">4315</td>
								<td align="left">110</td>
								<td align="left">6003</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</table>
				</table-wrap>
				<p>Analyses of different epidemiological aspects of the <italic>Candida</italic>
					species may assist in disease prevention, control and treatment. In our
					analysis, yeast colonisation was more frequently observed in renal transplant
					recipients and diabetic patients (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table
					2</xref>) than in the control group. This finding indicates that patients with
					altered immune responses are more susceptible to fungal infection, which is in
					agreement with (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Hogg et al. 2013</xref>). See
						<xref ref-type="table" rid="t3">Table 3</xref>. </p>
				<table-wrap id="t3">
					<label>Table 3</label>
					<caption>
						<title>Frequencies of raw materials according to their stratigraphic
							provenance. EU: stratigraphic unit. </title>
					</caption>
					<table>
						<colgroup width="20%">
							<col/>
							<col/>
							<col/>
							<col/>
							<col/>
						</colgroup>
						<thead style="background-color:#bebebe">
							<tr>
								<th align="left">Raw material</th>
								<th align="left">UE 1</th>
								<th align="left">UE 2</th>
								<th align="left">UE 3</th>
								<th align="left">UE 4</th>
							</tr>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<tr style="background-color:#f3f3f3">
								<td align="left">-</td>
								<td align="left">%</td>
								<td align="left">N</td>
								<td align="left">%</td>
								<td align="left">N</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td align="left">Gap hydrothermal alteration</td>
								<td align="left">3,97 14,39</td>
								<td align="left">186</td>
								<td align="left">1,88 18,42</td>
								<td align="center">6</td>
							</tr>
							<tr style="background-color:#f3f3f3">
								<td align="left">Andesite</td>
								<td align="left">2,23</td>
								<td align="left">15</td>
								<td align="left">1,49</td>
								<td align="center">0</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td align="left">Quartz</td>
								<td align="left">0,5</td>
								<td align="center">1</td>
								<td align="left">0,1</td>
								<td align="center">0</td>
							</tr>
							<tr style="background-color:#f3f3f3">
								<td align="left">Indeterminate</td>
								<td align="left">0,5</td>
								<td align="center">0</td>
								<td align="left">0</td>
								<td align="center">0</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td align="left">Total</td>
								<td align="left">100</td>
								<td align="left">1010</td>
								<td align="left">100</td>
								<td align="left">30</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</table>
				</table-wrap>
				<p>The high <italic>Candida</italic> colonisation observed in diabetic patients is
					correlated with multifactorial events that are influenced by factors such as
					high concentrations of sugars (sucrose, glucose and fructose) in tissues and low
					levels of salivary secretions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Fagan
					1999</xref>). A high frequency of colonisation in diabetic patients has been
					previously observed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Anderson et al.
					2007</xref>). In addition, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Andrefsky
					2010</xref>) reported that diabetes mellitus is one of the most common
					pathological disorders predisposing adult patients to the development of
					different clinical forms of candidiasis. </p>
				<p>Our results show that <italic>C. albicans</italic> was the most frequently
					isolated species among all patient groups (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t3">Table
						3</xref>). <italic>C. albicans</italic> is a yeast species of wide genetic
					variability and great adaptability to different anatomical sites, likely
					explaining its high frequency of isolation from human hosts (<xref
						ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Buc y Silvestre 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr"
						rid="B9">Johnson 1985</xref>). A clear example of this correlation between
					colonisation and pathogenicity is the fact that <italic>C. albicans</italic> is
					responsible for 90% of oral and oesophageal candidiasis episodes (<xref
						ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Andrefsky 1998</xref>) in <xref ref-type="fig"
						rid="f6">Figure 6</xref>.</p>
				<p>
					<fig id="f6">
						<label>Figure 6</label>
						<caption>
							<title>Tips Black Roof fractured projectile.</title>
						</caption>
						<graphic xlink:href="1678-8060-mioc-0074-02760160042-gf06.tif"/>
					</fig>
				</p>
				<p>Although <italic>C. albicans</italic> is still the most common pathogen involved
					in candidiasis, a significant increase in NAC infections has been observed
					recently (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Gambier 1993</xref>); in particular,
						<italic>C. glabrata</italic>, <italic>C. krusei</italic>, <italic>C.
						tropicalis</italic> and <italic>C. parapsilosis</italic> have been found to
					be etiological agents of disease (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Andrefsky
						1998</xref>). In our study, one-third of the isolates identified were NAC
					species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6">Figure 6</xref>). According to Andrefsky,
					increases in colonisation with NAC species are associated with extensive
					prophylactic use of antifungal drugs in immunocompromised patients. </p>
				<p>It was also observed that <italic>C. parapsilosis</italic> was frequently
					isolated as an accompanying species in the present study. This result
					corroborates the guidelines for the management of candidiasis as described by
						<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Buc y Silvestre (2006</xref>). Here, the
					authors classified <italic>C. parapsilosis</italic> as one of the most common
					agents of candidaemia in Latin America, in particular Brazil. This type of
					infection mainly affects hospitalised patients using central venous catheters in
						<xref ref-type="table" rid="t4">Table 4</xref>. </p>
				<table-wrap id="t4">
					<label>Table 4</label>
					<caption>
						<title>Traces of use stone tools. Ind: Not determined.</title>
					</caption>
					<table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
						<colgroup width="16%">
							<col/>
							<col/>
							<col/>
							<col/>
							<col/>
							<col/>
						</colgroup>
						<thead>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="2" align="center">Unidade stratigráfica</td>
								<td rowspan="2" align="center">Instrumento</td>
								<td colspan="2" align="center"
									style="border-bottom-width:thin;border-bottom-style:solid">Tipo
									de huellas</td>
								<td rowspan="2" align="center">Posible acción</td>
								<td rowspan="2" align="center">Sustancia</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td align="center">Anverso</td>
								<td align="center">Reverso</td>
							</tr>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="9" align="center">1</td>
								<td align="center">&#x00a0;</td>
								<td align="center">Microlascados</td>
								<td align="center">Microlascados</td>
								<td align="center">Corte</td>
								<td align="center">Ind.</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td align="center">&#x00a0;</td>
								<td align="center">Microlascados</td>
								<td align="center">Microlascados</td>
								<td align="center">Corte</td>
								<td align="center">Blanda</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td align="center">Lascas filo vivo</td>
								<td align="center">Microlascados</td>
								<td align="center">Microlascados</td>
								<td align="center">Ind.</td>
								<td align="center">Ind.</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td align="center">&#x00a0;</td>
								<td align="center">Microlascados</td>
								<td align="center">Microlascados</td>
								<td align="center">Raspado</td>
								<td align="center">Ind.</td>
							</tr>
							<tr style="border-bottom-width:thin;border-bottom-style:solid">
								<td align="center">&#x00a0;</td>
								<td align="center">Microlascados; abrasion</td>
								<td align="center">Abrasion</td>
								<td align="center">Corte</td>
								<td align="center">Ind.</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="2" align="center"
									style="border-bottom-width:thin;border-bottom-style:solid"
									>Raspadores</td>
								<td align="center">Microlascados</td>
								<td align="center">No presenta</td>
								<td align="center">Ind.</td>
								<td align="center">Ind.</td>
							</tr>
							<tr style="border-bottom-width:thin;border-bottom-style:solid">
								<td align="center">Microlascados</td>
								<td align="center">No presenta</td>
								<td align="center">Raspado</td>
								<td align="center">Dura</td>
							</tr>
							<tr style="border-bottom-width:thin;border-bottom-style:solid">
								<td align="center">Lasca retocada</td>
								<td align="center">Microlascados</td>
								<td align="center">No presenta</td>
								<td align="center">Ind.</td>
								<td align="center">Ind.</td>
							</tr>
							<tr style="border-bottom-width:thin;border-bottom-style:solid">
								<td align="center">Denticulado</td>
								<td align="center">Microlascados; abrasion</td>
								<td align="center">No presenta</td>
								<td align="center">Raspado</td>
								<td align="center">Dura</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="12" align="center">2</td>
								<td rowspan="10" align="center"
									style="border-bottom-width:thin;border-bottom-style:solid"
									>Lascas filo vivo</td>
								<td align="center">Microlascados</td>
								<td align="center">Microastillamiento</td>
								<td align="center">Corte</td>
								<td align="center">Blanda</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td align="center">Microlascados</td>
								<td align="center">No presenta</td>
								<td align="center">Raspado</td>
								<td align="center">Blando</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td align="center">Microlascados</td>
								<td align="center">Microlascados</td>
								<td align="center">Corte</td>
								<td align="center">Blando</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td align="center">Microlascados; abrasion</td>
								<td align="center">Abrasion</td>
								<td align="center">Raspado</td>
								<td align="center">Dura</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td align="center">Microlascados</td>
								<td align="center">Microlascados</td>
								<td align="center">Corte</td>
								<td align="center">Blanda</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td align="center">Microlascados</td>
								<td align="center">Microlascados</td>
								<td align="center">Ind.</td>
								<td align="center">Ind.</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td align="center">Microlascados</td>
								<td align="center">No presenta</td>
								<td align="center">Raspado</td>
								<td align="center">Dura</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td align="center">Microlascados; abrasion</td>
								<td align="center">Abrasión leve</td>
								<td align="center">Raspado</td>
								<td align="center">Dura</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td align="center">Microlascados; abrasion</td>
								<td align="center">Microlascados</td>
								<td align="center">Corte</td>
								<td align="center">Blanda</td>
							</tr>
							<tr style="border-bottom-width:thin;border-bottom-style:solid">
								<td align="center">Microlascados</td>
								<td align="center">Microlascados; abrasión</td>
								<td align="center">Corte</td>
								<td align="center">Blanda</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td rowspan="2" align="center">Lascas retocadas</td>
								<td align="center">Microlascados; desgaste leve </td>
								<td align="center">No presenta </td>
								<td align="center">Ind. </td>
								<td align="center">Ind. </td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td align="center">Microlascados; abrasion</td>
								<td align="center">No presenta</td>
								<td align="center">Raspado</td>
								<td align="center">Dura</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</table>
				</table-wrap>
				<p>In our study, certain epidemiological aspects, such as gender, age and
					candidiasis history, did not influence the colonisation of
						<italic>Candida</italic> species in the oral cavity of the analysed
					patients. These results confirm those of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Johnson
						1985</xref>, who determined that oral cavity colonisation was not associated
					with gender. Our results are also in agreement with studies by <xref
						ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Buc y Silvestre (2006</xref>), who did not observe
					an association between oral candidiasis and patient gender or age. Andrefsky
					suggests that increases in the frequency of oral candidiasis may be associated
					with poor oral hygiene, specific diets, use of dental prosthesis or other
					diseases of the oral mucosa (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t5">Table
					5</xref>).</p>
				<table-wrap id="t5">
					<label>Table 5</label>
					<caption>
						<title>Number of identified specimens (NISP NISP and%) by taxa according to
							their</title>
					</caption>
					<table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
						<colgroup width="14%">
							<col/>
							<col/>
							<col/>
							<col/>
							<col/>
							<col/>
							<col/>
						</colgroup>
						<thead>
							<tr style="border-bottom-width:thin;border-bottom-style:solid">
								<td>Unidad estratigráfica</td>
								<td colspan="2" align="center">1</td>
								<td colspan="2" align="center">2</td>
								<td colspan="2" align="center">Total</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Taxa</td>
								<td align="center">NISP</td>
								<td align="center">% NISP</td>
								<td align="center">NISP</td>
								<td align="center">% NISP</td>
								<td align="center">NISP</td>
								<td align="center">% NISP</td>
							</tr>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>Mammalia</td>
								<td align="right">11</td>
								<td align="right">1 1</td>
								<td align="right">55</td>
								<td align="right">14,1</td>
								<td align="right">66</td>
								<td align="right">13,5</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Rodentia</td>
								<td align="right">14</td>
								<td align="right">14</td>
								<td align="right">39</td>
								<td align="right">10</td>
								<td align="right">53</td>
								<td align="right">10,8</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Caprinae</td>
								<td align="right">2</td>
								<td align="right">2</td>
								<td align="right">0</td>
								<td align="right">0</td>
								<td align="right">2</td>
								<td align="right">0,4</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Canidae</td>
								<td align="right">1</td>
								<td align="right">1</td>
								<td align="right">3</td>
								<td align="right">0,8</td>
								<td align="right">4</td>
								<td align="right">0,8</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td><italic>Lama</italic> sp.</td>
								<td align="right">2</td>
								<td align="right">2</td>
								<td align="right">0</td>
								<td align="right">0</td>
								<td align="right">2</td>
								<td align="right">0,4</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td><italic>Pkyllotis</italic></td>
								<td align="right">1</td>
								<td align="right">1</td>
								<td align="right">3</td>
								<td align="right">0,8</td>
								<td align="right">4</td>
								<td align="right">0,8</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Akodon sp.</td>
								<td align="right">0</td>
								<td align="right">0</td>
								<td align="right">2</td>
								<td align="right">0.5</td>
								<td align="right">2</td>
								<td align="right">0,4</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td><italic>Spalacopus</italic> sp.</td>
								<td align="right">0</td>
								<td align="right">0</td>
								<td align="right">1</td>
								<td align="right">0.3</td>
								<td align="right">1</td>
								<td align="right">0.2</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Ave</td>
								<td align="right">1</td>
								<td align="right">1</td>
								<td align="right">0</td>
								<td align="right">0</td>
								<td align="right">1</td>
								<td align="right">0,2</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Passeriforme</td>
								<td align="right">2</td>
								<td align="right">2</td>
								<td align="right">7</td>
								<td align="right">1,8</td>
								<td align="right">9</td>
								<td align="right">1.8</td>
							</tr>
							<tr style="border-bottom-width:thin;border-bottom-style:solid">
								<td>Indeterminado</td>
								<td align="right">66</td>
								<td align="right">66</td>
								<td align="right">279</td>
								<td align="right">71,7</td>
								<td align="right">345</td>
								<td align="right">70,6</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Tolal</td>
								<td align="center">100</td>
								<td align="center">100</td>
								<td align="center">389</td>
								<td align="center">100</td>
								<td align="center">489</td>
								<td align="center">100</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</table>
					<table-wrap-foot>
						<fn id="TFN1">
							<p> stratigraphic provenance. </p>
						</fn>
					</table-wrap-foot>
				</table-wrap>
				<p>The genetic diversity among <italic>C. albicans</italic> isolates was analysed
						(<xref ref-type="table" rid="t5">Table 5</xref> y <xref ref-type="table"
						rid="t4">4</xref>), and the formation of two population groups was observed.
					Group A consisted of the largest number of isolates in this study, as well the
					type strain and strains from other Brazilian states. Group B included seven
					isolates and the strains LEMI7986E (KC905077/GB) and L8278 (KC408953/GB)
					belonging to UNIFESP University (São Paulo state) (<xref ref-type="bibr"
						rid="B1">Andrefsky 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Cartajena et
						al. 2007</xref>) in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t5">Table 5</xref>. Despite
					the formation of two groups, low genetic diversity was observed between the
					isolates collected from Paraná state (Federal University of Paraná) when
					compared to strains from different Brazilian states. It was also observed that
					specific phylogenetic groups were not formed based on the type of patient (renal
					transplant recipient, diabetic or control group). The two groups formed were
					98.8% similar with five polymorphic sites in the 412 bp analysed (four sites in
					the ITS region and one site in the 5.8S region). However, this last substitution
					is a mutation. Therefore, we suggest that regions other than ITS and 5.8S should
					be analysed for intraspecific studies of this group in <xref ref-type="fig"
						rid="f7">Figure 7</xref>. </p>
				<p>
					<fig id="f7">
						<label>Figure 7</label>
						<caption>
							<title>Bone instrument (A1, UE2 base), A. debitage active end at the
								apex; B. lascado in detail apex; C. striae apex; D. manufacturing
								grooves in the shaft.</title>
						</caption>
						<graphic xlink:href="1678-8060-mioc-0074-02760160042-gf07.tif"/>
					</fig>
				</p>
			</sec>
		</sec>
		<sec sec-type="discussion|conclusions">
			<title>Discusión y Comentarios</title>
			<p>Some studies have suggested that species of <italic>C. albicans</italic>, although
				isolated from different patients, can have low variability despite having very
				similar genomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Cartajena et al. 2007</xref>), <xref
					ref-type="fig" rid="f7">Figure 7</xref>. <italic>Candida</italic> spp, which is
				present in many different anatomical sites in the human body, may have passed from
				one individual to another as populations migrated; this would explain the low
				genomic variability observed. Additionally, some studies suggest that most
				individuals are colonised or infected by one single strain of
					<italic>Candida</italic>; more significant genetic differences may exist between
				isolates of different geographic origins. Large diversity in a population of
					<italic>C. albicans</italic> may be the result of different sources, as observed
				in the work. The low variability found among the <italic>C. albicans</italic>
				isolates in the present study could be explained by the geographic proximity of the
				patients, as was determined in studies by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Johnson
					(1985</xref>).</p>
			<p>A phylogenetic tree was formed using the sequences of seven different
					<italic>Candida</italic> species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7">Figure 7</xref>)
				and showed Clade A included the largest number of isolates (91.2%) and the majority
				of isolates from GenBank (71.4%). In conclusion, yeast colonisation of the oral
				cavity occurs more frequently in renal transplant recipients and diabetic patients
				than in healthy individuals. Sequences of ITS and rDNA regions were able to
				correctly identify <italic>Candida</italic> species and can be used for accurate
				species identification for this genus. <italic>C. albicans</italic> was the most
				frequently isolated species regardless of patient gender or age. The phylogenetic
				study showed that <italic>C. albicans</italic> isolates have low genetic diversity
				based on rDNA sequences, and the formation of two population groups was observed.
				However, these groups had no correlation with respect to gender, age or region of
				isolation.</p>
		</sec>
	</body>
	<back>
		<ack>
			<title>Acknowledgements</title>
			<p>Funded by: DEC 2007 SOC 13-2, University of Chile (CM), FONDECYT #1140824 (DJ and
				MC), Doctoral Fellowship Program Human Capital Advanced CONICYT - Chile 2011
				Scholarship (BS). We thank Messrs. Victor Prado, Luis Fuentes and Roberto Alvarez
				for permits granted for field work, Catherine Contreras, Francisco Vergara, Benjamin
				Ballester and Cristián Solar for their participation in the field and especially
				Daniel Pavlovic by ceramic analysis Natalie Hormazábal by functional analysis of
				lithic and two anonymous reviewers whose recommendations helped improve this
				work.</p>
		</ack>
		<ref-list>
			<title>Referencias Citadas</title>
			<ref id="B1">
				<mixed-citation>Andrefsky, W. 1998. <italic>Lithics, Macroscopic Approaches to
						Analysis</italic>. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge.</mixed-citation>
				<element-citation publication-type="book">
					<person-group person-group-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>Andrefsky</surname>
							<given-names>W.</given-names>
						</name>
					</person-group>
					<year>1998</year>
					<source>Lithics, Macroscopic Approaches to Analysis</source>
					<publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>
					<publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
				</element-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B2">
				<mixed-citation>Andrefsky, W. 2010. Human land use strategies and projectile point
					damage, resharpening and discard patterns. <italic>Human Evolution</italic>
					25:13-30.</mixed-citation>
				<element-citation publication-type="journal">
					<person-group person-group-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>Andrefsky</surname>
							<given-names>W.</given-names>
						</name>
					</person-group>
					<year>2010</year>
					<article-title>Human land use strategies and projectile point damage,
						resharpening and discard patterns</article-title>
					<source>Human Evolution</source>
					<volume>25</volume>
					<fpage>13</fpage>
					<lpage>30</lpage>
				</element-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B3">
				<mixed-citation>Anderson, G. D.; Sandweiss, K.A. (eds.) 2007. <italic>Climate Change
						and Cultural Dynamics: A Global Perspective on Holocene
					Transitions</italic>. Academic Press, San Diego.</mixed-citation>
				<element-citation publication-type="book">
					<person-group person-group-type="editor">
						<name>
							<surname>Anderson</surname>
							<given-names>G. D.</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Sandweiss</surname>
							<given-names>K.A.</given-names>
						</name>
					</person-group>
					<year>2007</year>
					<source>Climate Change and Cultural Dynamics: A Global Perspective on Holocene
						Transitions</source>
					<publisher-loc>Academic Press</publisher-loc>
					<publisher-name>San Diego</publisher-name>
				</element-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B4">
				<mixed-citation>Buc, N. y Silvestre, R. 2006. Funcionalidad y complementariedad de
					los conjuntos líticos y óseos en el humedal del nordeste de la Provincia de
					Buenos Aires: Anahí, un caso de estudio. <italic>Intersecciones en
						Antropología</italic> 7:129-146.</mixed-citation>
				<element-citation publication-type="journal">
					<person-group person-group-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>Buc</surname>
							<given-names>N.</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Silvestre</surname>
							<given-names>R.</given-names>
						</name>
					</person-group>
					<year>2006</year>
					<article-title>Funcionalidad y complementariedad de los conjuntos líticos y
						óseos en el humedal del nordeste de la Provincia de Buenos Aires: Anahí, un
						caso de estudio</article-title>
					<source>Intersecciones en Antropología</source>
					<volume>7</volume>
					<fpage>129</fpage>
					<lpage>146</lpage>
				</element-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B5">
				<mixed-citation>Cartajena, I. L.; Grosjean, N. M. 2007. Camelid domestication in the
					western slope of the Puna de Atacama, Northern Chile.
						<italic>Anthropozoologica</italic> 42:155-173.</mixed-citation>
				<element-citation publication-type="journal">
					<person-group person-group-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>Cartajena</surname>
							<given-names>I. L.</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Grosjean</surname>
							<given-names>N. M.</given-names>
						</name>
					</person-group>
					<year>2007</year>
					<article-title>Camelid domestication in the western slope of the Puna de
						Atacama, Northern Chile</article-title>
					<source>Anthropozoologica</source>
					<volume>42</volume>
					<fpage>155</fpage>
					<lpage>173</lpage>
				</element-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B6">
				<mixed-citation>Fagan, B. 1999. <italic>Floods, Famines, and Emperors: El Niño and
						the Fate of Civilizations</italic>. Pimlico, London.</mixed-citation>
				<element-citation publication-type="book">
					<person-group person-group-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>Fagan</surname>
							<given-names>B.</given-names>
						</name>
					</person-group>
					<year>1999</year>
					<source>Floods, Famines, and Emperors: El Niño and the Fate of
						Civilizations</source>
					<publisher-name>Pimlico</publisher-name>
					<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
				</element-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B7">
				<mixed-citation>Gambier, M. 1993. <italic>Prehistoria de San Juan</italic>. Ansilta
					Editora, San Juan.</mixed-citation>
				<element-citation publication-type="book">
					<person-group person-group-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>Gambier</surname>
							<given-names>M.</given-names>
						</name>
					</person-group>
					<year>1993</year>
					<source>Prehistoria de San Juan</source>
					<publisher-name>Ansilta Editora</publisher-name>
					<publisher-loc>San Juan</publisher-loc>
				</element-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B8">
				<mixed-citation>Hogg, A.Q.; Hua, P.G.; Blackwell, M.; Niu, C.E.; Buck, T.P.;
					Guilderson, T.J.; Heaton, J.G.; Palmer, P.J.; Reimer, R.W.; Reimer, C.S.M.;
					Turney, S.R.H. 2013. SHCAL13 Southern Hemisphere Calibration, 0-50,000 years CAL
					BP. <italic>Radiocarbon</italic> 55:1889-1903.</mixed-citation>
				<element-citation publication-type="journal">
					<person-group person-group-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>Hogg</surname>
							<given-names>A.Q.</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Hua</surname>
							<given-names>P.G.</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Blackwell</surname>
							<given-names>M.</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Niu</surname>
							<given-names>C.E.</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Buck</surname>
							<given-names>T.P.</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Guilderson</surname>
							<given-names>T.J.</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Heaton</surname>
							<given-names>J.G.</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Palmer</surname>
							<given-names>P.J.</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Reimer</surname>
							<given-names>R.W.</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Reimer</surname>
							<given-names>C.S.M.</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Turney</surname>
							<given-names>S.R.H.</given-names>
						</name>
					</person-group>
					<year>2013</year>
					<article-title>SHCAL13 Southern Hemisphere Calibration, 0-50,000 years CAL
						BP</article-title>
					<source>Radiocarbon</source>
					<volume>55</volume>
					<fpage>1889</fpage>
					<lpage>1903</lpage>
				</element-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B9">
				<mixed-citation>Johnson, E. 1985. Current developments in bone technology. En
						<italic>Advances in Archaeological Method and Theory Vol.</italic> 8, pp.
					157-235. Academic Press, Londres.</mixed-citation>
				<element-citation publication-type="book">
					<person-group person-group-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>Johnson</surname>
							<given-names>E.</given-names>
						</name>
					</person-group>
					<year>1985</year>
					<chapter-title>Current developments in bone technology</chapter-title>
					<source>Advances in Archaeological Method and Theory</source>
					<volume>8</volume>
					<fpage>157</fpage>
					<lpage>235</lpage>
					<publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>
					<publisher-loc>Londres</publisher-loc>
				</element-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B10">
				<mixed-citation>Kim, J.; Schneider, R.; Hebbeln, D.; Muller, P. y Wefer, G. 2002.
					Last deglacial sea-surface temperature evolution in the Southeast Pacific
					compared to climate changes on the South American continent. <italic>Quaternary
						Science Reviews</italic> 21:2085-2097.</mixed-citation>
				<element-citation publication-type="journal">
					<person-group person-group-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>Kim</surname>
							<given-names>J.</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Schneider</surname>
							<given-names>R.</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Hebbeln</surname>
							<given-names>D.</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Muller</surname>
							<given-names>P.</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Wefer</surname>
							<given-names>G.</given-names>
						</name>
					</person-group>
					<year>2002</year>
					<article-title>Last deglacial sea-surface temperature evolution in the Southeast
						Pacific compared to climate changes on the South American
						continent</article-title>
					<source>Quaternary Science Reviews</source>
					<volume>21</volume>
					<fpage>2085</fpage>
					<lpage>2097</lpage>
				</element-citation>
			</ref>
		</ref-list>
	</back>
</article>
