<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" specific-use="sps-1.5" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Braz Oral Res</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bor</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Brazilian Oral Research</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">Braz. oral res.</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1807-3107</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Pesquisa Odontológica -
          SBPqO</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/1807-3107BOR-2016.vol30.0007</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Maternal risk behavior and caries incidence in children with sickle
          cell disease</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Soares</surname>
            <given-names>Felipe Fagundes</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cangussu</surname>
            <given-names>Maria Cristina Teixeira</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Vianna</surname>
            <given-names>Maria Isabel Pereira</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Rossi</surname>
            <given-names>Thais Regis Aranha</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Carvalho</surname>
            <given-names>Anderson Santos</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Brito</surname>
            <given-names>Maria Goretti Silva</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1">
          <label>1</label>
          <institution content-type="original">Universidade Federal da Bahia - UFBA,
            Faculdade de Odontologia, Departamento de Odontologia Social e Pediátrica,
            Salvador, BA, Brazil.</institution>
          <institution content-type="normalized">Universidade Federal da
            Bahia</institution>
          <institution content-type="orgname">Universidade Federal da Bahia</institution>
          <institution content-type="orgdiv1">Faculdade de Odontologia</institution>
          <institution content-type="orgdiv2">Departamento de Odontologia Social e
            Pediátrica</institution>
          <addr-line>
            <named-content content-type="city">Salvador</named-content>
            <named-content content-type="state">BA</named-content>
          </addr-line>
          <country country="BR">Brazil</country>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>14</day>
        <month>02</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>30</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <elocation-id>e7691</elocation-id>
      <permissions>
        <license license-type="open-access"
          xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xml:lang="en">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the
            Creative Commons Attribution License</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <title>ABSTRACT:</title>
        <p>The aim of this study was to analyze the incidence of caries, in relation to
          maternal risk behaviors and clinical conditions representing different levels of
          sickle cell disease severity. A total of 295 children aged 6 to 60 months
          participated in this cohort conducted from August 2007 to December 2008. They
          were diagnosed and monitored by the referral service of the state. Interviews
          were made with families to identify sociodemographic variables, and an oral exam
          was performed to determine dental caries. The SRQ (Self Report Questionnaire)
          scale was used to diagnose the presence of common mental disorders, and the CAGE
          (Cut down, Annoyed, Guilty and Eye opener) was applied to determine abusive use
          of alcohol. The absolute and relative frequencies of the variables of interest
          were analyzed by Chi-square and Mann-Whitney, with a 5% significance level. The
          incidence variables were analyzed according to the logistic regression model,
          with a confidence interval of 95%. Caries incidence (1.98; SD = 4.68) was higher
          in the HbSS genotype. There was a statistically significant association between
          caries incidence and both abusive use of alcohol (32.43%, RR = 1.99; 1.05-3.78;
          95%CI) and common mental disorders (8.77% RR = 0.37; 0.15-0.93; 95%CI). There
          was also an association between caries incidence and maternal risk behavior,
          indicating that the care network should be expanded to include patients with
          sickle cell disease.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
        <title>Key words:</title>
        <kwd>Oral Health</kwd>
        <kwd>Dental Caries</kwd>
        <kwd>Anemia</kwd>
        <kwd>Sickle Cell</kwd>
        <kwd>Cohort Studies</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Sickle cell anemia (SCA) is the most prevalent hemoglobinopathy in
          Brazil<sup>(</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref><sup>)</sup>. It is
        estimated that 3500 new cases are diagnosed each year. Bahia has the highest
        prevalence of sickle cell disease (1:650) <sup>(</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1"
          >1</xref><sup>)</sup> of all the Brazilian states. SCA is hereditary,
        characterized by autosomal recessive genes, and is caused by a mutation on
        chromosome 11. This leads to a structural modification responsible for changes in
        the stability, solubility and structure of erythrocytes, which take on a sickle
        shape when exposed to low oxygen tension, acidosis or dehydration <sup>(</sup><xref
          ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref><sup>), (</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3"
          >3</xref><sup>), (</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref><sup>)</sup>.</p>
      <p>Pediatric patients usually have a history of multiple hospitalizations for pain
        crises, episodes of severe anemia, blood transfusions and recurrent periods of
        pulmonary infections. Children constitute the age group most vulnerable to severe
        symptoms, especially when diagnosed with the HbSS genotype <sup>(</sup><xref
          ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref><sup>)</sup>.</p>
      <p>In the oral cavity, SCA can cause diastemata, delays in tooth eruption,
          <sup>(</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref><sup>), (</sup><xref
          ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref><sup>), (</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7"
          >7</xref><sup>)</sup> malocclusion and glossitis. <sup>(</sup><xref
          ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref><sup>), (</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7"
          >7</xref><sup>), (</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref><sup>),
          (</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref><sup>)</sup> There are no studies
        in the literature containing conclusive data related to the prevalence of caries and
        periodontal disease in children afflicted by SCA, <sup>(</sup><xref ref-type="bibr"
          rid="B10">10</xref><sup>), (</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1"
          >1</xref><sup>)</sup> despite the existence of biological plausibility for an
        association between incidence of caries and severity of the disease.</p>
      <p>It is reported that the quality of life and the children’s family situation are
        critical in determining the process of health and disease. <sup>(</sup><xref
          ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref><sup>)</sup> The greater incidence of dental
        caries in children is connected to a poorly structured family context, as well as
        worse health conditions in socially marginalized areas.<sup>(</sup><xref
          ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref><sup>)</sup> These phenomena are also observed
        in regard to the impact that a chronic illness has on a family. <sup>(</sup><xref
          ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref><sup>)</sup> A worse family context can be
        observed when the mother is an alcoholic or/and has a common mental disorder.
          <sup>(</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref><sup>)</sup> Both conditions
        characterize maternal risk behaviors, <sup>(</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2"
          >2</xref><sup>), (</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref><sup>)</sup> and
        are associated with a higher caries experience in children. <sup>(</sup><xref
          ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref><sup>), (</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5"
          >5</xref><sup>)</sup>
      </p>
      <p>The aim of this study was to associate dental caries incidence to maternal risk
        behaviors and clinical conditions representing the levels of severity of this
        disease (presence of HbSS genotype, occurrence of pain crises, need for
        hospitalization and blood transfusions) by performing six-month follow-up studies on
        children aged 06-60 months, diagnosed and monitored by the state of Bahia’s referral
        service from August 2007 to December 2008.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="methods">
      <title>Methodology</title>
      <p>A prospective cohort study was conducted. The population was established in August
        2007 with children aged at least 6 months, who did not present with a history
        showing clinically severe conditions (hospitalization and blood transfusion) and
        were regularly monitored by the <italic>Serviço de Hematologia da Divisão de Triagem
          Neonatal</italic> of <italic>Associação dos Pais e Amigos dos
          Excepcionais</italic> - APAE (the Association of Parents and Friends of
        Exceptional Children) in Salvador-BA, the only service accredited by the
          <italic>Ministério da Saúde</italic> - MS and the <italic>Secretaria de Saúde da
          Bahia</italic> - SESAB as a referral center for the treatment, diagnosis and
        screening of neonates in the state.</p>
      <p>The inclusion criteria comprised a minimum age of six months, diagnostic confirmation
        of sickle cell disease, at least two clinical consultations at the health service
        with an interval of at least 6 months - when interviews/caries examinations were
        conducted - and complete information regarding both the children’s primary risk
        variables and the outcome variable. The exclusion criteria comprised inability to
        meet the above requirements and refusal to participate in the study. A total of 409
        children, 41.9% of the initial sample, were excluded after missing appointments
        scheduled by the referral service. These cases made it difficult to perform a
        follow-up, and, consequently, presented a bias in the survey.</p>
      <p>In all, 295 children were followed until December 2008, representing one year and 6
        months for this cohort. Each child was assessed twice with an average interval of 8
        months. The exams and the interview took place during the child’s regular visit to
        the health service.</p>
      <p>After signing the terms of informed consent, parents or guardians were asked
        questions related to socioeconomic status (skin color, family income, level of
        maternal education, age of mother and child, marital status), sickle-cell-related
        clinical conditions (morbidity in the last six months, pain crises, hospitalization
        and blood transfusion, as well as the genotype of the disease); and maternal risk
        behavior (common mental health disorders, alcohol abuse).</p>
      <p>The genotype was informed by the child’s guardian and confirmed by the medical
        records. “Common mental health disorder” was diagnosed if eight or more questions on
        the Self Report Questionnaire - SRQ-20<sup>(</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6"
          >6</xref><sup>)</sup> received a positive response. In respect to the variable
        of “alcohol abuse,” a positive response to two or more questions on the CAGE
          scale<sup>(</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref><sup>)</sup> indicated
        its consideration. These questionnaires were validated in previous studies carried
        out in Brazil. <sup>(</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref><sup>),
          (</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref><sup>)</sup>
      </p>
      <p>While awaiting their appointment with the hematologist, the children participated in
        oral health education activities (supervised brushing and guidance on oral hygiene)
        and were examined for dental caries according to the criteria established by the
        Oral Health Brazil<sup>(</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref><sup>)</sup>
        survey.</p>
      <p>A change in the child’s health status was considered an incidental event. In relation
        to dental caries, this meant the development of another manifestation of the
        disease; in relation to the clinical conditions assessed and the variables related
        to maternal behavior, it meant any new events. </p>
      <p>The data were collected by three trained and previously calibrated teams.
        Verification of inter-examiner and intra-examiner conformity identified a general
        agreement of 98% for caries and a kappa of 0.79. </p>
      <p>The absolute and relative frequencies of the variables of interest were analyzed
        using the Chi-square test. The Mann-Whitney tests measured the probability of a
        statistically significant difference between the median dmft - the number of
        decayed, missing and filled teeth - at baseline and at follow-up, as well as the
        probability of association between the median incidence of caries and the genotype.
        In this case, individuals who did not have the HbSS and HbSC genotypes were
        excluded. A significance level of 5% was used in these tests.</p>
      <p>The association measure used was relative risk (RR) with a confidence interval of
        95%. The main outcome was dichotomized (individuals with new caries = 1; individuals
        without new caries = 0). The variables that were associated with the outcome in the
        univariate model, and that showed a p-value less than or equal to 0.05, were
        analyzed using the multiple Poisson regression model.</p>
      <p>The data was tabulated using Epi Info 6.04<sup>&#x00ae;</sup> (CDC, Atlanta, USA),
        and the statistical analysis was performed using Stata<sup>&#x00ae;</sup>, version
        12.0 (StataCorp LP, College Station, USA).</p>
      <p>The research protocol for the study was submitted to and approved by the Research
        Ethics Committee of the <italic>Maternidade Climério de Oliveira</italic>
          (<italic>Universidade Federal da Bahia</italic> - UFBa), under number 014/2007.
        There are no conflicts of interest with the institution where the research was
        conducted (APAE/Salvador). </p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>A total of 295 children were followed. Their ages ranged from 6 to 60 months, with a
        mean age of 32.92 months (SD = 17.31). Of this total, 145 were males (49.15%) and
        150 were females (50.85%). Most were classified as brown (54.80%), residing in the
        countryside (76.62%), and with a family income below the minimum wage (74.40%). As
        for genotype, 33.78% were HbSS, 51.35% were HbSC and 14.87% belonged to other
        genotypes of less clinical relevance, and, for this reason, were not detailed in
        this investigation.</p>
      <p>In respect to the children’s family setting, the mother’s average age was 26 years;
        54.36% of the mothers had completed elementary and middle school, and 76.41% were
        married or had a common-law union with a partner. During the study period, 19.32% of
        new cases of common mental disorders and 12.54% of new cases of maternal alcohol
        abuse were identified in this group.</p>
      <p>The variables for the clinical manifestations of the disease, <italic>i.e.</italic>,
        presence of pain crises, need for hospitalization and blood transfusion, showed an
        incidence of 22.03%, 14.92% and 8.47%, respectively. The degree of clinical
        vulnerability of the studied population becomes more evident when observing that a
        respective 70.85% (pain crisis), 55.17% (hospitalization) and 28.73% (blood
        transfusion) of the patients had a history of these events occurring at least once
        from the baseline through the entire study period, according to the morbidity.</p>
      <p>Description of dmft according to sickle cell condition showed that the HbSS group had
        a greater incidence of caries than the HbSC. There was no statistically significant
        association between the incidence of caries and the genotype (p-value = 0.34). On
        the other hand, there was a statistically significant difference between the
        baseline median dmft values (0.00, 0.00-0.00) and the follow-up values (0.00,
        0.00-2.00) (p-value = 0.00), revealing an increase in caries not associated with the
        genotype of the disease over time.</p>
      <p>Among the variables that represent clinical severity, the occurrence of a pain crisis
        as a risk factor was associated to the higher incidence of caries only in the crude
        analysis (RR = 1.89, 95%CI 1.01-3.58). In relation to maternal behavior variables,
        maternal alcohol abuse (RR = 1.90, 95%CI 1.11-3.25) and common mental disorders (RR
        = 0.40, 95%CI 0.17-0.98) were associated to outcome. These results were confirmed in
        the adjusted model.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>This study examined the caries incidence, clinical conditions and maternal risk
        behavior of 295 children between 6 and 60 months of age, with sickle cell disease,
        who were followed in a six-month cohort. No cohort studies were found in the
        literature which examined the clinical conditions and the family context; moreover,
        none related the impact of these conditions to the oral health of this group group
          (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref> e <xref ref-type="table"
          rid="t2">Table 2</xref>).</p>
      <table-wrap id="t1">
        <label>Table 1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Measures of central tendency and dispersion dmft second most significant
            genotypes of sickle cell disease in children 6-60 months in Bahia.</title>
        </caption>
        <table>
          <colgroup width="33%">
            <col/>
            <col/>
            <col/>
          </colgroup>
          <thead style="background-color:#e6e7e8">
            <tr>
              <th align="left">Sickle cell disease condition+</th>
              <th align="center">n</th>
              <th align="center">dmft<sup>&#x2020;</sup> SD Median(Q1-Q3)</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="center">HbSS</td>
              <td align="center">116</td>
              <td align="center">0.90 2.14 0.00(0.00-0.00)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center">HbSC</td>
              <td align="center">138</td>
              <td align="center">0.65 1.74 0.00(0.00-0.00)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center"> </td>
              <td align="center">n</td>
              <td align="center">dmft<sup>&#x2020;</sup> SD Median (Q1-Q3)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center">HbSS</td>
              <td align="center">116</td>
              <td align="center">2.69 5.23 0.00(0.00-2.75)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center">HbSC</td>
              <td align="center">138</td>
              <td align="center">1.87 4.75 0.00(0.00-0.25)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center">-</td>
              <td align="center">n</td>
              <td align="center">dmft<sup>&#x2020;</sup> SD Median (Q1-Q3)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center">HbSS</td>
              <td align="center">116</td>
              <td align="center">1.98 4.68 0.00(0.00-0.75)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center">HbSC</td>
              <td align="center">138</td>
              <td align="center">1.65 4.51 0.00(0.00-0.00)</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="TFN1">
            <p>dmft - mean of decayed, missing and filled teeth. <sup>+</sup>41
              individuals, both at baseline, as the follow-up represent other
              genotypes of sickle cell disease not evaluated in this association.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot>
      </table-wrap>
      <table-wrap id="t2">
        <label>Table 2</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Analysis of crude and adjusted risk relative (RR) between caries
            incidence and severity of clinical variables and maternal risk behavior in
            children aged 6 to 60 months with sickle cell disease in Bahia (n =
            295).</title>
        </caption>
        <table frame="hsides" rules="none">
          <colgroup width="20%">
            <col/>
            <col/>
            <col/>
            <col/>
            <col/>
          </colgroup>
          <thead style="border-bottom-width:thin;border-bottom-style:solid">
            <tr>
              <th align="left">n %</th>
              <th align="left">-</th>
              <th align="left">Caries incidence </th>
              <th align="left">RR (95%CI) Crude</th>
              <th align="left">RR (95%CI) Adjusted**</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">Pain crisis</td>
              <td align="left">46</td>
              <td align="left">22.01</td>
              <td align="left">1.89(1.01-3.58)</td>
              <td align="justify">1.88(0.95-3.73)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">Hospitalizations</td>
              <td align="left">10</td>
              <td align="left">22.73</td>
              <td align="left">1.24(0.68-2.27)</td>
              <td align="center">-</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">No</td>
              <td align="left">46</td>
              <td align="left">18.33</td>
              <td align="center">1.00</td>
              <td align="left">-</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">Transfusions</td>
              <td align="left">4</td>
              <td align="left">16.00</td>
              <td align="left">0.83(0.33-2.11)</td>
              <td align="center">-</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">Abusive use of alcohol</td>
              <td align="left"> </td>
              <td align="left">32.43</td>
              <td align="left">1.90(1.11-3.25)</td>
              <td align="justify">1.99(1.05-3.78)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">No 44</td>
              <td align="left"> </td>
              <td align="left">17.05</td>
              <td align="center">1.00</td>
              <td align="center">1.00</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">Common mental disorder</td>
              <td align="left">-</td>
              <td align="left">-</td>
              <td align="left">0.40(0.17-0.98)</td>
              <td align="justify">0.37(0.15-0.93)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">No 51 21.43</td>
              <td align="left">-</td>
              <td align="left">-</td>
              <td align="center">1.00</td>
              <td align="center">1.00</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="TFN2">
            <p>RR obtained by multivariate poisson regression analysis.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>It is difficult to compare the results regarding oral health, because there are no
        other caries incidence studies in patients with sickle cell disease. Only two
        articles were found in the literature that investigated dental caries in children
        with sickle cell disease, both of which are cross-sectional studies. One described
        the clinical and oral health conditions, the socioeconomic status and the family
        context of 704 children in the state of Bahia, Brazil,<xref ref-type="bibr"
          rid="B10">10</xref> and the other associated caries prevalence to socioeconomic
        status in 160 children in Recife, Brazil.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">11</xref>
        The dmft in these studies was 0.94 (DP = &#x00b1;2.28) and 2.12, respectively. In
        the National Oral Health Survey (SB Brazil) of 2003, <sup>(</sup><xref
          ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref><sup>)</sup> the mean dmft for healthy
        Brazilian children aged 18-36 months was 1.07 (SD = 2.40) and 1.00 (SD = 2.24) in
        the northeast region. As for the 5 year-old age group, the dmft recorded in the SB
        Brazil 2010<sup>(</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref><sup>)</sup> was 2.43
        (95%CI 2.22-2.63) for the country and 1.70 (95%CI 1.36-2.04) for the city of
        Salvador, the Bahia state capital where the research was conducted. In the present
        study, the dmft of the follow-up group (2.69, SD = 5.23) was higher than that of
        Brazil and that of Bahia.</p>
      <p>According to the literature, <sup>(</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2"
          >2</xref><sup>), (</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref><sup>)</sup>
        sickle cell disease does not predispose individuals to caries, at least not
        directly. In the two articles found in the literature referred to above, there was
        no statistically significant association between caries incidence and genotype. HbSS
        showed a higher caries incidence, as was observed in other studies with
          adults<sup>(</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref><sup>), (</sup><xref
          ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref><sup>)</sup> and adolescents, <sup>(</sup><xref
          ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref><sup>)</sup> as compared with the HbSC
        genotype and control groups. Ralstrom<sup>(</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1"
          >1</xref><sup>)</sup> attributed this association to the lower severity of
        clinical manifestations of the HbSC <italic>versus</italic> the HbSS genotype.</p>
      <p>Despite the lack of association between the incidence of caries and the genotype for
        more severe disease, it was found that the morbidity for pain crises was a risk
        factor for caries incidence. Pain crisis is the most common clinical event and the
        primary reason for seeking medical services and hospitalization; <sup>(</sup><xref
          ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref><sup>)</sup> for this reason, the children
        reporting this symptom in this study were considered as having a greater degree of
        severity than those who never presented it. Pain crisis was the event that most
        contributed to a greater burden of disease on Cameroonian parents. <sup>(</sup><xref
          ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref><sup>)</sup>
      </p>
      <p>In respect to this severe clinical profile, Guimarães and collaborators, in their
        study on the daily lives of families of children and adolescents with sickle cell
        disease, reported that mothers tend to be overprotective and burdened when they need
        to spend time caring for their children and have to give up social functions. An
        impact on the family environment was also reported in this study, namely the
        inability to accept the disease and the fear of death, to the extent that the family
        experienced periods of greater or lesser control of the disease and could not handle
        the situation, feeling lost and hopeless.</p>
      <p>According to Martin and Angelo, <sup>(</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7"
          >7</xref><sup>)</sup> the mother is largely responsible for family health in
        low-income communities, since she represents the center of the family. It is the
        mother who plays the leading role in controlling important variables which determine
        caries, such as eating habits and oral hygiene. Accordingly, the variables related
        to maternal behavior - the presence of common mental disorders and alcohol abuse -
        are important factors in constructing the family context. In this study, maternal
        risk behavior variables were associated with caries incidence. This goes to show how
        family background affects the oral health of these children.</p>
      <p>Sousa <italic>et al</italic>. also found an association between family dysfunction,
        resulting from common maternal mental disorder symptoms and alcoholism, and the
        incidence of caries in children aged 2-3 years with a dmft of 0.72 (SD = 1.8). </p>
      <p>It has been suggested that sickle cell disease, its social representations and its
        clinical symptoms, which tend to worsen with age, are factors that trigger and/or
        contribute to building a negative family environment, and, consequently, to a
        worsening in oral health.</p>
      <p>Despite the relevance of sickle cell disease to the general and oral health of
        stricken children, the limitations of this study are worth noting, including the
        convenience of the sample, which consisted of those requiring health services and
        already receiving medical and dental care. As a result, it is important to note that
        the sample does not allow inference of these results to all patients with sickle
        cell disease, only to the sample population.</p>
      <p>Another consideration is that that sample size represented not only a limitation, but
        also a difficulty, since case follow-up was dependent on the patients’ return for a
        follow-up appointment with the hematologist. Thus, the sample may not have been
        enough for some variables to become more expressive. Furthermore, the strategy of
        bivariate analysis for caries incidence was adopted because caries was the most
        important oral manifestation, but further studies should not discard the existence
        of other associations.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>In this sample, an association between the incidence of caries and maternal behavior
        (alcohol abuse, maternal depression) was verified. The results also give indications
        of the association between sickle cell disease severity and a higher caries
        incidence, a finding that should be followed up in subsequent studies to confirm
        this relationship.</p>
      <p>The significant loss of patients between the baseline and the follow-up suggests that
        there may be significant barriers in accessing the state’s referral center. Studies
        on the access to these services still lack in the literature, indicating that
        further evaluation is required.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>We would like to thank <italic>Associação dos Pais e Amigos dos Excepcionais</italic>
        - APAE/Salvador for their support and collaboration. This study was funded by the
          <italic>Fundação de Amparo à Pesquisa do Estado da Bahia</italic> - FAPESB.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation>De Franceschi L, Corrocher R. Established and experimental
          treatments for sickle cell disease. Haematologica.
          2004;89(3):348-56.</mixed-citation>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>De Franceschi</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Corrocher</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Established and experimental treatments for sickle cell
            disease</article-title>
          <source>Haematologica</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>89</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>348</fpage>
          <lpage>356</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation>Fonseca MA, Oueis HS, Casamassimo PS. Sickle cell anemia: a review
          for the pediatric dentistry. Pediatr Dent. 2007;29(2):159-69.</mixed-citation>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fonseca</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oueis</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Casamassimo</surname>
              <given-names>PS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sickle cell anemia a review for the pediatric
            dentistry</article-title>
          <source>Pediatr Dent</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>159</fpage>
          <lpage>169</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation>Alves PV, Alves DK, Souza MM, Torres SR. Orthodontic treatment of
          patients with sickle cell anemia. Angle Orthod.
          2006;76(2):269-73.</mixed-citation>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Alves</surname>
              <given-names>PV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alves</surname>
              <given-names>DK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Souza</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Torres</surname>
              <given-names>SR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Orthodontic treatment of patients with sickle cell
            anemia</article-title>
          <source>Angle Orthod</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>76</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>269</fpage>
          <lpage>273</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation>Martins MF, Costa JS, Saforcada ST, Cunha MD. Quality of the
          environment and associated factors: a pediatric study in Pelotas, Rio Grande do
          Sul, Brazil. Cad Saude Publica. 2004;20(3):710-8.
          doi:10.1590/S0102-311X2004000300007</mixed-citation>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Martins</surname>
              <given-names>MF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Costa</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saforcada</surname>
              <given-names>ST</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cunha</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Quality of the environment and associated factors a pediatric
            study in Pelotas, Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil</article-title>
          <source>Cad Saude Publica</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>710</fpage>
          <lpage>718</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0102-311X2004000300007</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation>Almeida TF, Vianna MI, Cabral MB, Cangussu MC, Floriano FR. Family
          context and incidence of dental caries in preschool children living in areas
          covered by the Family Health Strategy in Salvador, Bahia State, Brazil. Cad
          Saude Publica. 2012;28(6):1183-95. doi:
          10.1590/S0102-311X2012000600017</mixed-citation>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Almeida</surname>
              <given-names>TF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vianna</surname>
              <given-names>MI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cabral</surname>
              <given-names>MB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cangussu</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Floriano</surname>
              <given-names>FR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Family context and incidence of dental caries in preschool
            children living in areas covered by the Family Health Strategy in Salvador,
            Bahia State, Brazil</article-title>
          <source>Cad Saude Publica</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>1183</fpage>
          <lpage>1195</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0102-311X2012000600017</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation>Masur J, Monteiro MJ. Validation of the "CAGE" alcoholism screening
          test in a Brazilian psychiatric inpatient hospital setting. Braz J Med Biol Res.
          1983;16(3):215-8.</mixed-citation>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Masur</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Monteiro</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Validation of the "CAGE" alcoholism screening test in a Brazilian
            psychiatric inpatient hospital setting</article-title>
          <source>Braz J Med Biol Res</source>
          <year>1983</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>215</fpage>
          <lpage>218</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation>Ministério da Saúde. Projeto SB Brasil 2003: condições de saúde
          bucal da população brasileira 2002-2003: resultados principais. Brasília, DF:
          Ministério da Saúde, 2004.</mixed-citation>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <collab>Ministério da Saúde</collab>
          </person-group>
          <source>Projeto SB Brasil 2003: condições de saúde bucal da população brasileira
            2002-2003: resultados principais</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <publisher-loc>Brasília, DF</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Ministério da Saúde</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation>Ralstrom EF. The impact of sickle cell disease on oral
          health-related quality of life. Pediatr Dent. 2014;36(1):24-8.</mixed-citation>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ralstrom</surname>
              <given-names>EF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The impact of sickle cell disease on oral health-related quality
            of life</article-title>
          <source>Pediatr Dent</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>24</fpage>
          <lpage>28</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation>Loureiro MM, Rozenfeld S, Portugal RD. Acute clinical events in
          patients with sickle cell disease: epidemiology and treatment. Rev Bras Hematol
          Hemoter. 2008;30(2):95-100. doi:
          10.1590/S1516-84842008000200005</mixed-citation>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Loureiro</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rozenfeld</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Portugal</surname>
              <given-names>RD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Acute clinical events in patients with sickle cell disease
            epidemiology and treatment</article-title>
          <source>Rev Bras Hematol Hemoter</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>95</fpage>
          <lpage>100</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1516-84842008000200005</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation>Wonkam A, Zameyo C, Mbanya D, Ngogang J, Ramesar R, Andwafo FF.
          Psychosocial burden of sickle cell disease on parents with an affected child in
          Cameroon. J Genet Couns 2014;23(2):192-201. doi:
          10.1007/s10897-013-9630-2.</mixed-citation>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wonkam</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zameyo</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mbanya</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ngogang</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramesar</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andwafo</surname>
              <given-names>FF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Psychosocial burden of sickle cell disease on parents with an
            affected child in Cameroon</article-title>
          <source>J Genet Couns</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>192</fpage>
          <lpage>201</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10897-013-9630-2</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
