<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Kitchen sink with a reduced strict set of JATS tags -->
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN"  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article article-type="sample" dtd-version="1.1d3" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <front>
    <article-meta>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Turn Word documents into structured <italic>JATS</italic> with Texture</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Michael Aufreiter</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Substance"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <string-name>Oliver Buchtala</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Substance"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Substance">Substance Software GmbH, Linz, Austria</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <!-- only one abstract element is considered in Author mode -->
      <abstract>
        <p>This is an <bold>article abstract</bold>, with a single paragraph</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p id="p1">Texture is a tool for publishers for creating structured JATS documents based on <bold>Word</bold> or InDesign submissions. Texture is developed by the Substance Consortium (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">[1]</xref>) formed by the Public Knowledge Project (PKP), the Collaborative Knowledge Foundation (CoKo) and Érudit.</p>
      <p>The tool is available as open source on Github (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">[2]</xref>) and</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2">
      <title>Create a bibliography</title>
      <p>Below is a list of unstructured references. Use the <bold>tag tool</bold> to turn them into bibliographic entries. After tagging you can cite them from within the text.</p>
      <p>Albert I, Mavrich TN, Tomsho LP, Qi J, Zanton SJ, Schuster SC, et al. 2007. Translational and rotational settings of H2A.Z nucleosomes across the Saccharomyces cerevisiae genome. Nature 446:572–6.</p>
      <p>Altman-Price N, Mevarech M. 2009. Genetic evidence for the importance of protein acetylation and protein deacetylation in the halophilic archaeon Haloferax volcanii. J Bacteriol 191:1610–7.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <!-- only the first ref-list element is considered in Author mode -->
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="bib1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bailey KA, Pereira SL, Widom J, Reeve JN. 2000. Archaeal histone selection of nucleosome positioning sequences and the procaryotic origin of histone-dependent genome evolution. J Mol Biol 303:25–34.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib2">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Altschul SF, Gish W, Miller W, Myers EW, Lipman DJ. 1990. Basic local alignment search tool. J Mol Biol 215:403–10.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
